A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards, Series O FA324
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards, Series O
1899-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller, David
Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison), 1874-1960
Rockefeller, John D., III (John Davison), 1906-1978
Rockefeller Foundation
FA324
21.09 Cubic Feet 55 letter document boxes, 1 half-letter document box.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr. C Business Interests D Civic Interests E Cultural Interests F Economic Reform Interests G Educational Interests H Friends and Services I Homes J Housing Interests K Medical Interests L Real Estate M Maps and Memorabilia N Religious Interests O Rockefeller Boards P Welfare - General Files Q World Affairs R Welfare - Youth Files S Documents T Public Relations U Public Land Law Review Commission V Greenrock W Properties X Costume Collection Y Media Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Arrangement note
This series is arranged alphabetically by the organization, or board. There are 14 sections, as follows:
John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Board, Bureau of Social Hygiene, China Medical Board, Davison Fund, General Education Board, International Education Board, International Health Commission, Rockefeller Brothers Fund, Rockefeller Foundation, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, Rockefeller Sanitary Commission, Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial, Spelman Fund of New York, Sealantic Fund.
Scope and Contents note
The Boards represented in this series are the most important philanthropies that have been developed from the Rockefeller fortune: the Bureau of Social Hygiene; the China Medical Board of the Rockefeller Foundation and its successor, the China Medical Board, Inc.; the Davison Fund; the General Education Board; the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; the Rockefeller Brothers Fund; the Rockefeller Foundation; the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now known as Rockefeller University); the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission; the Sealantic Fund; and the Spelman Fund of New York.
The papers in the Rockefeller Boards series document the implementation of Frederick T. Gates's vision of systematic and focused philanthropic activities that became the hallmark of Rockefeller philanthropies. These materials document the earliest history of these philanthropies and the participation of family members and their advisors in the founding and ongoing operations of these organizations.
The Rockefeller Boards material is a crucial addition to several of the collections of organizational records housed at the Rockefeller Archive Center. The collections to which these papers are a particularly important complement are the Rockefeller Foundation Archives, especially Record Group 3 - Administration, Program and Policy, and Record Group 4 - China Medical Board; the General Education Board; the Bureau of Social Hygiene; the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; and the John D. Rockefeller Papers.
For each organization, the materials include the charter and certificate of incorporation; minutes of meetings of the Board of Directors, if a Rockefeller family member was a trustee or director; general correspondence between the administrators of the board and the Rockefeller family office; and subject folders containing correspondence, reports, and other documents on issues and events which were significant to the board. Also found in this series are materials on John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Board, which recommended to Mr. Rockefeller the general direction and specific recipients of his personal giving.
The family members who figure most prominently in this series are John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, and David Rockefeller. John D. Rockefeller, Nelson Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, and Winthrop Rockefeller also appear. Of the Rockefeller family advisors who appear, Starr J. Murphy and Thomas M. Debevoise are the most prominent.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA314 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Public health; Prohibition; Public policy; Public health administration; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Education -- United States; Education; Economics; Economic policy; Government policy; Folk art; Federal government -- United States; Family planning; Public relations; Housing rehabilitation; Health insurance; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Restoration and conservation; Religious institutions; Religion; Public welfare; Travel; United States; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; World War I; World War II; Urban policy; Urban renewal; Philanthropy -- United States; Performing arts; New York (State); Parks -- New York (State); Medical sciences; New York (N.Y.); Medical education; Medical research; Maternal health services; Medical care; International relations -- United States; Juvenile delinquency; International education; International relations; International economic relations; International cooperation; Civic improvement; Child welfare; Charities -- Investments; Charities; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charitable contributions; Capital investments; Philanthropy; Business enterprises, Foreign; Business; Arts; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art, Modern; Art; Economic development
- John D. Rockefeller Jr's Advisory Committee
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - General, 1919-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Advisory Committee setup; conferences with John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; appropriations to Committee. Committee expenditures, reports, agendas, memoranda, policies, problems, replacements. Staley's 1926 report on Committee. Routine administrative details. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson, Arthur Woods, Thomas M. Debevoise, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, Raymond B. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, F. S. Staley, B. Houston.
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - General, 1932-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Form Letters, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Form letters in English, French, and German.
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Reports, 1914-1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Annual operating reports of both Advisory and Special Advisory Committee; annual appropriation reports; reports on commitments.
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Reports, 1925-1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Reports, 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, January-June 1934 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, July 1934-1937 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Special Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1922-1925 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Special Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1926-1927 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Special Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Special Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Special Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Special Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Special Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Special Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Advisory Committee - Special Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Bureau of Social Hygiene
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - American Vigilance Association, 1912-1914 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    Group interested in combating prostitution; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions to budget and cost of re-publication of Chicago Vice Commission Report. Friction within Association; plans for re-organization. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, Clifford Roe, Charles Eliot, Marion Dodd, Grace Dodge, James Reynolds, George Kneeland.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Bedford Reformatory - General, 1911-1916 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    Bureau of Social Hygiene financed building of laboratory of social hygiene at Bedford; plans for scientific study of prostitution and criminology among women; report on first 100 cases; annual reports. Creation of division for mentally defective female delinquents. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest in work. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Katharine Bement Davis, Starr J. Murphy, Raymond B. Fosdick, Nicholas M. Butler, Jane Addams, Charles O. Heydt.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Bedford Reformatory - General, 1917-1926 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Not Used (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Bedford Reformatory - Authorizations, Extras and Statements, 1912-1913 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    Bids for construction of new building for Laboratory of Social Hygiene. Correspondents include Katharine Bement Davis, Jerome D. Greene, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Bedford Reformatory - Pledge of Funds, 1912-1917 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. underwrote cost of establishing criminology institute. Correspondents include Robert W. Gumbel, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Katharine Bement Davis.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Bedford Reformatory - Psychopathic Hospital - Correspondence, 1915-1918 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    Approval of plans and specifications; payment of expenses incurred. Correspondents include Katharine Bement Davis, Simon Flexner, Charles O. Heydt, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Bedford Reformatory - Taxation, 1916-1924 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    Efforts to secure exemption from taxation for John D. Rockefeller, Jr.-owned Bedford Hills property; eventual conveyance of property to State of New York. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Starr J. Murphy, Charles O. Heydt.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Marcus Braun - Grand Jury, 1903-1910 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    Braun's notes on constitution of New York Independent Benevolent Association, and on control of prostitutes in Europe; reports on investigation of white slave traffic in American cities. Correspondents include James Reynolds, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Marcus Braun.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Chicago Vice Commission - Committee of Fifteen, 1911-1925 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    Committee report; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s commendation of their work. Correspondents include Simon Flexner, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond B. Fosdick.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Committee of Fourteen, 1901-1933 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    New York committee investigating prostitution; special studies of colored prostitution problem in Harlem, role played by night clubs and speak-easies. Proposed amalgamation with Prophylaxis Society; dissolution of Committee. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Frederick Whitin, Raymond B. Fosdick, Charles O. Heydt, Willard S. Richardson.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Committee of Fourteen - Contributions, 1911-1929 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    List of Guarantors; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s payment of subscription to Guarantee Fund. Contributions for special investigations on suppression of Raines Law Hotels; reports on various investigations.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Committee of Three - Clifford G. Roe, 1911-1912 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    Hiring of Roe; report on lists of resorts of prostitution in New York. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Charles O. Heydt, C. G. Roe.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Committee of Three - Paul M. Warburg, J. H. Schiff, 1911-1916 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    Warburg's contribution to Bedford work; his resignation as director; Dr. Flexner's letters to Committee via John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include Dr. Flexner, Paul M. Warburg, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Dr. Katharine Bement Davis, 1918-1933 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    Dr. Davis's appointment to General Medical Board of Council of National Defense; memo outlining plan of federation for support of New York Jewish philanthropic societies; studies of reformatories and female delinquents in New York state. Summary of work and publications of Bureau of Social Hygiene; appropriations for special research projects and trip to Europe; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution for chapel at women's prison. Preparation of book on sex life of women. Correspondents include Dr. Katharine Bement Davis, Abraham Flexner, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, Robert W. Gumbel, Arthur Woods, Raymond B. Fosdick, Ruth Topping.
  - Not Used (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Dr. Katharine Bement Davis - Dance Halls Survey, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution for survey of New York City dance halls.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Dr. Katharine Bement Davis - Housing Conditions, 1921 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    Bureau of Social Hygiene financed study of housing conditions of employed women in New York City; publication of report.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Dr. Katharine Bement Davis - Ten-Year Contract, 1917-1930 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    Dr. Davis resigned from Parole Board of New York City; was hired as full-time Bureau of Social Hygiene staff member. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution for her salary; disbanding of organization; agreement to allow Dr. Davis to complete her studies.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Dr. Katharine Bement Davis - Study of Sex Life, 1920-1923 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s appropriation to work of committee inquiring into sex life of married women. Correspondents include Dr. Katharine Bement Davis, Charles O. Heydt, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Dr. Katharine Bement Davis - Study of Sex Life - Sex Research Work, 1921-1927 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    Employment of Earl Zinn for research project; preliminary report of research committee; budget.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Drug Addiction Control, 1915-1929 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    Colonel Woods's article on traffic in narcotics; Hadley's comments and criticisms. Role of Bureau of Social Hygiene in signing of international drug treaty, 1931; proposed drug hospital at Riker's Island; reports of Committee on Drug Addiction; special projects undertaken by Bureau of Social Hygiene. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge on behalf of Bureau of Social Hygiene for intensive study of drug addiction; study to determine legal use of drugs; budgets. Correspondents include Morris Hadley, Arthur Woods, Thomas M. Debevoise, Dr. Katharine Bement Davis, Charles O. Heydt, Raymond B. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Drug Addiction Control, 1930-1934 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Raymond B. Fosdick, 1912-1920 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    Fosdick's trip to Europe to study organization, personnel and administration of European police paid for by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. through Bureau of Social Hygiene. Fosdick's resignation as Commissioner of Accounts; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution to detective agency to apprehend and convict participants in Rosenthal murder. Denial of allegations that John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s funds supported disorderly house; Raymond B. Fosdick's book; wartime work. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Raymond B. Fosdick, Charles O. Heydt, Bertram Cutler.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - James B. Reynolds, 1916-1920 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    Reynolds owned disreputable property; termination of his connection with Bureau of Social Hygiene.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Dr. Abraham Flexner, 1911-1926 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    Letters introducing Mr. Flexner; study of prostitution in Europe; Mr. Flexner's book on subject, translated into several languages. Formation of Bureau of Social Hygiene library. Correspondents include Abraham Flexner, Charles O. Heydt, Starr J. Murphy, Raymond B. Fosdick, Dr. Katharine Bement Davis, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Grand Jury - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1909-May 1910 (Box 8, Folder 56)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. accepted position as Foreman of Grand Jury; requested information about investigation of white slave trafficking. Court's charge to the Grand Jury; jury's resolution on presentment; statement to newspapers, judge and court. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Walter H. Page, Jacob Riis, Arthur Brisbane, Charles O. Heydt, Starr J. Murphy, James Reynolds.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Grand Jury - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., June 1910-1913 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Grand Jury - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - Presentment, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Proposals Prior to Incorporation, July-October 1910 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    Suggested names for Mayor's Commission; letters about what work of commission should be; sending of R. W. Kaufman's book, "The House of Bondage." Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond B. Fosdick, Edward Harkness, George F. Peabody, Edward Bok, Seth Low.
  - Bureau of Social Hygiene - Proposals Prior to Incorporation, November 1910-1911 (Box 8, Folder 60)